<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe instruction for all families to be brought vp in the knowledge of their duetie to God, and one to another: and to be taught in the hope of saluation in Christe Jesus.</title>
            <author>S. S., fl. 1583.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1583</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11255</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21518</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102601</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838373</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838373</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2749</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11255)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2749)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1116:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe instruction for all families to be brought vp in the knowledge of their duetie to God, and one to another: and to be taught in the hope of saluation in Christe Jesus.</title>
                  <author>S. S., fl. 1583.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[by T. Dawson] for William Ponsonby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1583.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: S.S.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B(-B8).</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Examinations, questions, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2749:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2749:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A briefe inſtruction for all Families, to be brought vp in the knowledge of their duetie to God, and one to another: and to be taught in the hope of ſaluation in Chriſte Ieſus.</p>
            <bibl>
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.</bibl>
            <q>4. Heare (O Iſrael) the Lord thy God is Lord only:</q>
            <q>6. And theſe wordes which I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund thee this day, ſhall bee in thy heart.</q>
            <q>7. And thou ſhalt rehearſe them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually vnto thy children, and ſhalt talke of them when thou tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieſt in thy houſe, &amp; as thou wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt by the way, and when thou lyeſt downe, and when thou riſeſt vp.</q>
            <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="motto">
               <body>
                  <q>
                     <l>Sperando ſpiro.</l>
                     <l>Operando deſpero.</l>
                  </q>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>S. S.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>¶ Imprented at London, for Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Ponſonby. 1583.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2749:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2749:2"/>
            <head>To the Church of God, in Walſingham, beloued in Chriſte, and called to be Saints: grace, mercy, and the hope of ſaluation, from God the Father, thorough Chriſt Ieſus his Sonne, be multiplyed vnto you.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S your place hath beene be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (my brethren) famous<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or rather for Idolatry infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous: <hi>non tam nobilis, quàm nota,</hi> not ſo noble as notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: ſo woulde I nowe, (if I were able) perſwade you, to redeeme, and purchaſe a new the loſſe of that long time ſo euilly ſpent: with the gain of greater knowledge, and more conſcionable practiſe, in old and young of that glorious Goſpell, which now thorough Gods mercies hath driuen away ignoraunce, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened your heartes, beegotten you to GOD, taught you his feare, and whereof you haue no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hold, then at the <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 21. 33.</note> will of the Lord. If <hi>Epheſus</hi> muſt redeeme the time ſpente in the honour of Diana, and <note n="b" place="margin">Acts. 19. 28.</note> diſhonour of God, which walking now in the <note n="c" place="margin">Ephe. 5. 17.</note> knowledge of his will: what price thinke you of repentaunce muſt VValſingham lay downe, to recouer the loſſe of thoſe daies, in the worſhip of an Idoll<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and neglect of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice? If Adam be <note n="d" place="margin">Gene. 3. 17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> curſſed, for pleaſing his owne fancie, and diſpleaſing God: how ſharpe a curſſe thinke you, deſerued that ſerpent, that firſt <note n="e" place="margin">Gene. 3. 4.</note> enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him herunto? If Iſrael did ſmart for Idolatrie, by whoring at <note n="f" place="margin">1. King. 12.</note> Bethel: ſhall <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eroboam</hi> goe free, that moued them to ſinne? If the dayes of <hi>Ioſiah</hi> muſt <note n="g" place="margin">2. King. 23.</note> mourne, for the time of his Fathers: what
<pb facs="tcp:2749:3"/>
teares muſt <hi>Manaſſes</hi> ſhed that cauſed them to erre? And if all places in this land had neede to lament the filthie Idolatries of the former ages: how much more oughteſt thou (<hi>VValſingham</hi>) bewaile, that haſt reached foorth that Cup of poyſon to infect them with all? The braſen Serpent was (<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. King. 18. 4.</note>) pouldred to duſt, as the inſtrument of the peoples fall: feare leaſt God in iudgement make thee as duſt, whiche haſt cauſed many to ſlumber in their ſinnes. The Temple, and houſe of that Idoll Baal was (<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. King. 10. 27</note>) broken downe, and the Lord in his hoate diſpleaſure made thereof a place of vile vſe: thou haſt been the ſeat and throne of many Balimes. Feare thou, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent: leaſt the Lord in his firie wrath, make of thy proude ſhrine of Satan, a poore and miſerable cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. Thou haſt ſhaken the ſtate, and enchaunted the mindes of kings, and princes, with the banefull dregges of mens inuentions: Nowe nouriſhe the ſoules of thy children that are in thee, with that (<note n="k" place="margin">Pet. 2. 2.</note>) ſincere milke of Gods holy worde: thou haſt been the puddle to defile thouſandes, now become that ſame <hi>Betheſda</hi> (<note n="l" place="margin">hn. 5. 2.</note>) to heale thy ſelfe: thou haſt beene to Englande as the waters of (<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od. 15. 23.</note>) <hi>Marah</hi> to Iſrael, now ſweeten thy ſelfe with the tree of life: thou haſt been to all inhabitants as the vnfruitfull wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of (<note n="n" place="margin">Kings. 2. 19.</note>) <hi>Hiericho,</hi> now become ſeaſoned with the ſalt of grace: thou haſt by thy former filthineſſe, drawne many to Hel: repent thee of that, and now let thy (<note n="o" place="margin">atth. 5. 16.</note>) light ſhine foorth, to call many to God. To conclude, thou haſt been the very (<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue. 16. 2.</note>) foule cage of all hatefull and vglie birdes: now pray and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour that thou maieſt become the happie hauen, &amp; ſafe harborough of all godlineſſe, and integritie of life.</p>
            <closer>Amen.
Thine to doe thee good.
<signed>S. S.</signed>
Sperando ſpiro.
Operando deſpero.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="instruction">
            <pb facs="tcp:2749:3"/>
            <head>A briefe inſtruction for Families.</head>
            <p>VVHo made you?</p>
            <p>A. God. <hi>Ge. 1. 27. Pſa. 95. 7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is God?</p>
            <p>A. He is an heauenly ſpirit, almighty, &amp; inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſible. <hi>Apoc. 18. Ioh. 4. 24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. How many gods are there?</p>
            <p>A. There is but one God. <hi>Ephe. 4. 6. Eſay 44. 6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What are thoſe then that are ſet vp by men?</p>
            <p>A. They are no Gods but vaine Idols, <hi>Pſal. 96. 5. 115. 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. How manie perſons are there?</p>
            <p>A. Three. <hi>1. Ioh. 5. 7. Ioh. 14. 26.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. By what name doe you call them?</p>
            <p>A. God the father, God the ſonne, and God the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Mat. 28. 19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. How are theſe one God, and yet three perſons?</p>
            <p>A. They are one in ſubſtance, and three in perſons.</p>
            <p>Q. What is the ſonne?</p>
            <p>A. Ieſus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chriſt both God and man. <hi>Ioh. 1. 1. 14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is the holy Ghoſt?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2749:4"/>
A. A diuine ſubſtance proceeding from the Father, &amp; the Son. <hi>Ioh. 14. 26. Act. 5. 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What doe you attribute to the father?</p>
            <p>A. The creation of me, and all the worlde. <hi>Math. 10. 29. Iohn. 5. 17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What vnto God the Sonne?</p>
            <p>A. The redemption of me, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde. <hi>1. Pet. 1. 18. 19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What vnto the holy Ghoſte?</p>
            <p>A. The dayly worke of holyneſſe in mee. <hi>1. Cor. 12. 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. Wherefore were you made?</p>
            <p>A. To glorifie God, by doing of his will. <hi>Ephe. 2. 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What briefe contents haue you of his will?</p>
            <p>A. The ten Commandements. <hi>Mat. 19. 17</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. Rehearſe them.</p>
            <p>A. <hi>God ſpake theſe words, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What meaneth this preface?</p>
            <p>A. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhe weth me, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe are the lawes of the eternal God, who both for his maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, &amp; his mercy, ought to be obeied. <hi>De. 28. 1. 15.</hi> Q. What is the meaning of this firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: <hi>Thou ſhalt haue, &amp;c?</hi> Herein doth God charg me, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of way, I eſteeme more of any thing,
<pb facs="tcp:2749:4"/>
then of him, or ſet by any ſo much, as by him. <hi>Hier. 17. 5. Leu. 14. 26.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is the meaning of this ſecond commandement? <hi>Thou ſhalt not, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Herein I am forbidden, to make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of any creature that is in any place, either to worſhippe it, or God in it, or ſo much as to thinke the incomprehenſible maieſtie of the euerliuing GOD to be like vnto it. <hi>Deut. 4. 15. 16. 17. 18. Rom. 1. 22. 23. Eſa. 40. 18. 25.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is the meaning of theſe words? <hi>Thou ſhalt not bow. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Here am I forbidden to worſhip, or in any religious manner to ſerue the work of other mens handes, or any of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God, though that I my ſelf ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Exo. 23. 24. 25. Hie. 10. 5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is the meaning of theſe words, <hi>For I the Lord thy God, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Herein he threatneth puniſhment to the obſtinate, and mercy to the obedient. <hi>Deu. 29. 19. 20 Eſai. 1. 19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is the meaning of this third co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement: <hi>Thou ſhalt not take, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Herein am I ſtraitly charged, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I doe not any way abuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorious maieſty of God, either in my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon talke, by ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,
<pb facs="tcp:2749:5"/>
curſing, or teſting, or in wicked practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uring, witching, enchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting, and ſuch like. <hi>Zach. 5. 3. 4. Leuit. 24. 14. 15. 16. Rom. 12. 14. Ephe. 4. Apoc. 21, 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is the meaning of this fourth commandement, <hi>Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber thou keep?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Herein am I charged y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the day which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord hath appointed for his ſeruice to be kept holy, be not by me either in ordinary bu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſines, &amp; works, or in idle places &amp; paſtimes prophaned: but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> therein I bee occupied in prayer, giuing of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks, hearing of his word &amp; the due receiuing of his ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to reſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne. <hi>Hier. 17. 21. 22. Ro. 12. 12. 1. Theſ 5. 18 Eſay. 58. 13. Act. 20. 7. Heb. 4 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is the meaning of this fift com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, <hi>Honor thy father, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Herein doth God ſtraightly charge, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> all ſubiects to their gouernours, people to their miniſters, childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to parents, ſeruants to maſters pupilles to their tutors, &amp; other to their ſuperiours, giue all reuerence, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; duty: &amp; theſe again in their callings to their inferiours, as by Gods worde they are bound. <hi>Leuit. 19. 32. Ro, 12. 7. 1. pet. 2. 13. 14. 17. 18. Col. 4. 1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is the meaning of this ſixt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement,
<pb facs="tcp:2749:5"/>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Herein God ſtraightly forbiddeth all kind of murder &amp; hurt, either in hart, tong, or deed. <hi>Deu. 19. 6. Mat. 5. 22. Pſa. 109. 17. Deu. 19. 11. 12. 13.</hi> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth that in all theſe three, we preſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> life &amp; good name of our neighbour. <hi>Pro. 31. 8, Pſal. 7. 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is the meaning of this ſeuenth commandement. <hi>Thou ſhalt not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Herein god forbiddeth al kind of filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, either in thoght, word, or deed. <hi>1. The. 4. 5. Col. 3. 8. Eph. 5. 5.</hi> and commandeth in all theſe three to liue vnſpotted. <hi>1. Theſ. 4. 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is the meaning of this eight commandement: <hi>Thou ſhalt not &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Herein god forbiddeth all wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gful poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or hindering of other mens goods by any means. <hi>Le. 19. 11. Pr. 20. 23.</hi> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth euery one to preſerue to the proper vſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> owner: and euery one to bee content with his eſtate. <hi>Exod. 23. 4. 5. Phil. 4. 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is the meaning of this nienth commandment: <hi>Thou ſhalt not beare &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Heerin God forbideth al lying, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling: <hi>Pro. 19. 5. 9.</hi> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth euery one to ſpeake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his heart. <hi>Eph. 4. 25.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is the meaning of this tenth commandement: <hi>Thou ſhalt couet?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2749:6"/>A. Heerein God forbiddeth euen the firſt beginnings &amp; motions vnto ſinne: <hi>Act. 8. 22. Pro. 6. 18.</hi> and commaundeth al pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie &amp; vprighnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heart. <hi>Deut. 10. 16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What are you briefly taught in al theſe?</p>
            <p>A. My dutie to God, and to my neighbor, <hi>Luke. 10. 27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. Are you not ſtraightly bounde to doe the ſame'<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yes, moſt ſtraightly. <hi>Deut. 8. 1. Mat. 7. 12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. And are you able of your ſelf ſo to do?</p>
            <p>A. No, not any way. <hi>Rom. 7. 18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is then the puniſhment for brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of them?</p>
            <p>A. Euerlaſting condemnation in hell fire: <hi>Deut. 27. 26. Mat. 5. 19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. Why then, are all condemned?</p>
            <p>A. No, a remna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t are ſaued. <hi>Mat. 7. 21. Ro. 11. 6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. By whome?</p>
            <p>A. By Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Ioh. 3. 16. 1, Tim. 1. 15</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. How hath he ſaued you?</p>
            <p>A. In that he fulfilled the law. <hi>Ioh. 19. 30.</hi> and was put to death for mee. <hi>Ro. 5. 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. Who are thoſe remnant that ſhall bee ſaued?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2749:6"/>A. They that truely repent and beleeue in him. <hi>Ioh. 3. 18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is a true repentance?</p>
            <p>A. It is a heartie ſorrowing for ſinnes paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed, with a hope of pardon, and an earneſt purpoſe of amendment. <hi>Mat. 3. 8. 9. Ioel 23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What is a true beliefe?</p>
            <p>A. It is a full aſſurance, and heartie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, grounded on the promiſes of God, that Chriſt Ieſus is wholy mine, &amp; I his. <hi>Heb. 11. 1. Gal. 3. 7. 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. Rehearſe the principles of your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe?</p>
            <p>A. <hi>I beleeue in God, the father almightie, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meaning of this: <hi>I beleeue in God &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. I doe heerein aſſure my ſelf, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god of all power, and creator of all things, is vnto me a prouident father. <hi>Pſa. 100. 2.</hi> &amp; <hi>23. 1. Act. 17. 28.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What of this: <hi>and in Ieſus Chriſte his only ſonne our Lorde?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. I doe heerein aſſure my ſelf, that Ieſus Chriſt is very God of his father, <hi>Ioh 1. 14. 1. Cor. 8. 6.</hi> &amp; that he hath redeemed
<pb facs="tcp:2749:7"/>
vs to be a people peculiar to himſelf. <hi>2. Tit. 14. Act. 20. 28.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is the meaning of this: <hi>Which was conceaued by, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Herein I aſſure my ſelfe that Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus being conceiued not by ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is ſinfull, but by the holy Ghoſt, is free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne. <hi>Ioh. 3. 6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What of this: <hi>Borne of the virgine Mary?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Heerein I beeleeue that Ieſus Chriſte is very man, and toke that fleſh of Mary, and yet ſhe a pure virgin. <hi>Eſay, 7. 14. Gal 4. 4. Rom. 1. 3. Ioh. 1. 14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What meane you by this: <hi>Suffered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Pontius Pilate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Herein I beleeue that Ieſus Chriſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered many thinges at the handes of the Iewes, that man <hi>Pontius Pilat</hi> beeing <hi>1. Pet. 2. 32. Mat. 27. 18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What meane you by this: <hi>Crucified, dead, and buried?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. In this I doe beleeue, that he was nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on a croſſe, and thereupon died, and in token of his death, he alſo was buried in the earth. <hi>Ioh. 19. 18. 30. 42.</hi> and all this was done, that he might deliuer mee
<pb facs="tcp:2749:7"/>
from the curſe of God, and euerlaſting death. <hi>Gal. 3. 13. Rom. 8. 32.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What meane you by this: <hi>Deſcended into Hell?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. I doe beleeue heerein that he ſuffered all the torments of Hell, which were due to me for ſinne, and alſo was holden downe of the ſame death for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpace of 2. daies, that he might get the victorie ouer it for euer. <hi>Pſal. 18. 5. 4. Act. 2. 24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meaning of this: <hi>The third day he roſe againe from &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. I beleeue herein that Ieſus Chriſt hath ouercome death, and hell, and in token thereof did riſe out of the graue the third day after his paſſion, who alſo is the firſt fruites of our reſurrection: <hi>Mat. 28. 6. Col. 2. 13. 15. 1. Cor. 15. 4. 20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is the meaning of this: <hi>Aſcended vp into heauen?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Heerin I beleeue, that Ieſus Chriſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he roſe from death, did in the ſight of men go up into heauen, that through him wee alſo which are his members, might aſcend thyther. <hi>Mar. 16. 19. Ioh. 14. 19.</hi> and 2. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2749:8"/>Q. What meane you by this: <hi>ſitteth on the right hand of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. I beleeue in this, that he now beeing in heauen, hath all glory, power and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion giuen vnto him ouer all thinges: which is meant by ſitting at the right hand, <hi>Mark 16. 19. Ro. 8. 3. 4. Phil. 2. 9. 10. 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is the meaning of this: <hi>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce he ſhall come to iudge &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. I beleeue in this, that Chriſt Ieſus ſhal come againe in bodie at the ende of the world, &amp; ſhal cal to iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t euery work bee it good or bad, both of thoſe which ſhall be liuing at his comming, &amp; which ſhall bee dead before: <hi>Eccle. 12. 14. 2, Tim. 4. 1 Ioh. 5. 25.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What beleeue you in this: <hi>I beleeue in the holy ghoſt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Herein I beleeue, that the third perſon in trinitie (the holy Ghoſte is God) and that hee is the worker of all the graces of God, in men, and ſanctifieth vs vnto all goodnes. <hi>Mat. 28. 19, Actes. 5. 3. 4. 1 Cor. 12. 3. 13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What do you meane by this: <hi>the holy Catholike Church:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2749:8"/>A. I beleeue in this, that God by Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus hath purchaſed to himſelfe, a congre gation, or flocke, profeſſing faith in his name, holy, and vnſpotted, which church is not now only included within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of Iurie as afore time, but is general of euery nation and place whatſoeuer. <hi>Eph. 5. 25, 26. 27<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Gal. 3. 28. Ephe. 2. 12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What meane you by this: <hi>Communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſaints?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. I beleeue herein, that there is &amp; ought to bee a mutuall communicating in this holy fellowſhip, of ſuche thinges as they haue receiued from God, to the help one of another. <hi>Eſay. 2. 3. 1 Pet. 4. 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What by this: <hi>forgiuenes of ſinnes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. I doe beleeue, that vnto them which are of this holy fellowſhip, there is through Ieſus Chriſte for all ſinnes forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to the repentante. <hi>Pſal. 103. 3. Actes. 10. 43.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What meane you by this <hi>the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the bodie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. I beleeue heerein, that my bodye which ſhall turne into duſt from whence it was taken: ſhall againe at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Chriſt, through him bee raiſed out of
<pb facs="tcp:2749:9"/>
the graue, &amp; ioyned with my ſoule. <hi>Ioh. 6. 39. 40.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is this: <hi>The life euerlaſting?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Herein I beleeue, that after this life, as many as die in the faith of Chriſte, ſhall riſe again to an eternall and happy life, whoſe ioyes no tongue can expres. <hi>Ioh. 3. 16. 1. Cor. 2. 9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. Howe come you by this faith?</p>
            <p>A. It is Gods gift. <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. 8. Ioh. 6. 24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. By what ordinarie meanes doth he giue it?</p>
            <p>A. By the preaching of his moſt holy word <hi>Rom. 10. 17. Ioh. 8. 47</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What call you the word of God?</p>
            <p>A. The Lawe, the preaching of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, the goſpel of Chriſt, and doctrine of the Apoſtles, conteined in the old and new Teſtament: <hi>Heb. 1. 1. Iohn. 6. 68 1. Pet. 1. 25.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. How is that faith ſealed vp in you?</p>
            <p>A. By the due receiuing of the ſacraments. <hi>1 Cor. 11. 26. Act. 2. 41.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. What is a Sacrament?</p>
            <p>A. It is an inſtitution of the Lord, hauing an outwarde, and uiſible ſubſtaunce, repreſenting an inuiſible grace vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2749:9"/>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How did God deliuer this lawe vnto his ſeruant Moſes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Written in two tables of ſtone.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements are there in the firſt table?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Foure Commandements.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What doo theſe foure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements teach vs?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Our dutie towards God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How many Commandements are in the ſecond table?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Sixe Commandements.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What doo theſe ſixe commandements teach vs?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Our dutie to our neighbour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> VVhy is the dutie to God, ſet before the dutie to our neighbour?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe wee ſhould ſerue him aboue all things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> And why art thou taught thy dutie to thy neighbour?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That it might be knowen whether I doe my dutie to God, or no.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How many Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts be there?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Ten.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Which be they?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God ſpake theſe wordes and ſayd.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2749:10"/>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Is this a commandement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No. but a preface vnto them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What learneſt thou by theſe wordes then?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I learne that God was the author of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> So, then I perceiue thou doeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it to be Gods word?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yea that doe I.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> VVhat doeſt thou gather in thoſe wordes? I am the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By this word, Lord, I gather that he is of power to puniſh the offenders.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What comfort haue wee in theſe? which brought thée out of the lande of Egypt, out of the houſe of bondage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I gather this comfort, that God is the deliuerer of me and all the faithfull from hell, as he deliuered Iſrael from Egypt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What doeſt thou learne by this commandement? Thou ſhalt haue none other Gods but me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I learne hereby to reioyce onely in the Lorde God, and to reſt in him one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What ſhall we ſay of thoſe that truſt
<pb facs="tcp:2749:10"/>
in Saintes and Angels, and make them as interceſſors to God for them? doe they fulfill this commandement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They can not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How ſo?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they reſt not onely in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> In the ſecond commandement why doth God forbid the making of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and the likeneſſe of any other thing?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they diſhonour him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> In that he forbiddeth vs to knéele be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them or to worſhip them: what would he haue vs to do?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To worſhip the Lord God onely and ſerue him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How ſhould he be worſhipped?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In ſpirite and in trueth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> VVhy doth God call himſelfe a gea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous God viſiting the ſinnes of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To ſhew his anger againſt Idolaters</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What call you Idolaters?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thoſe which maintaine ſuperſtitious doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How doth the Lord promiſe to ſhewe
<pb facs="tcp:2749:11"/>
himſelfe to ſuch as loue him, and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour themſelues to kéepe his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He will be mercifull to ſuch.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What art thou commanded in the third commandement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I am commanded reuerently to vſe the name of God, in all my doings that I goe about.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What are you forbidden to doe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All ſwearing, curſing and banning of any thing that he hath made.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> If a man or woman, whether it be, call God to record in a falſe matter: doth he vſe Gods name reuerently?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, but calleth him to be his conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How is the Sabboth day kept holy?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In hearing &amp; learning the holy word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> It is apparant that in this fourth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement is expreſſed to kinds of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, the one of the bodie, the other of the minde, the one earthly the other heauenly, are both theſe labours forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in this commandement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, but the one.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> VVhich is forbidden?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2749:11"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> The bodely labour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Then thou confeſſeſt that the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all &amp; heauenly labour ought to be done: what ſhould wee ſéeke for in this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly labour?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The kingdom of heauen and the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What ſhall we ſay of thoſe that will not come at the Church to learne the way to heauen and to vnderſtande the right pointes of Gods lawe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Such regarde not Gods commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> In the fift co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth this word honor?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To honour, is to obey, feare, relieue and ſerue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What meaneth this worde? father and mother.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By father and mother I vnderſtande all that haue any office or authoritie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> As how for example?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> As the Prince ouer the people, the maieſtrates ouer the places where they rule, the miniſters ouer their charge or pariſh, the maiſters and dames ouer
<pb facs="tcp:2749:12"/>
their ſeruants, fathers and mothers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Doeſt thou hereby acknowledge that thoſe that are ouer others, ſhould teach them that are vnder them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They ought to learne Gods word to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end they might teach others y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Ought not the ſubiects, towneſmen, ſeruants, and children to be diligent in learning of Gods word?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yea, if not, they diſobey Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandemet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> VVhy is the promiſe of long life ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to this commandement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To encourage vs vnto the better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of our dutie in obeying.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> In this ſixt commaundement, Thou ſhalt doe no murther, doth God onely forbid the outward act of murther, and not alſo the conſent vnto murther?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yea, he forbiddeth the conſent vnto murther.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Doth it forbid nothing elſe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It alſo forbiddeth vs anger &amp; malice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What doe thoſe that reuile, mocke &amp; deſpiſe others be they neuer ſo ſimple?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Such doe alſo againſt this comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2749:12"/>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What ſay you of pride, ſurfetting and dronkennes, whether be they murther or not?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateſt kind of murther.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How ſo?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they hurt the ſoule and doe great diſhonor to God which made vs to ſet forth his glorie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> In the vij. commandement, Thou ſhalt not commit adulterie, what doth the Lord require at our hands?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To kéepe our bodies as fit veſſels for the holy Ghoſt to dwell in.</p>
            <p>Q. Doth he only forbid the outward fact of whoredome and adulterie?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He forbiddeth vs the very thought and enticement to ſuch lewdnes, as well as the outward fact.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What meaneth this eight comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That I ſhould refraine from hurting any, by taking from them that which is theires.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Doth this worde ſteale ſignify no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but taking away and robbing?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yea: if I kéepe from another that
<pb facs="tcp:2749:13"/>
which he hath laboured for, I ſteale be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I giue him not his duetie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What are we commanded?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To liue a contented life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What ſhal we ſay of thoſe that kéepe the knowledge of Gods worde from the ſimple and ignorant, which Chriſt would haue to be taught?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Such alſo ſteale, becauſe they doe withhold the truth. <hi>Ioh. 10. 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What art thou taught by this ninth commandement, Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I am taught to ſpeake nothing but truth, neither for the loue nor hatred of any.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What doe you ſay of lyers, ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and ſuch as are buſie bodies, med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of ſuch thinges as they haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do withall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Such regarde not this law of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What is this tenth commandement, Thou ſhalt not couet thy neighbours houſe, wife, goodes, ſeruant, nor any thing els which is his?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is a bridle vnto my minde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What learneſt thou to doe by it?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2749:13"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> To refraine from wiſhing any thing at all to my neighbours hurt or hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, be it neuer ſo ſmall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> VVhat is the ſhort ſunune and effect of the terme Commandements?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To loue God aboue all thinges, and my neighbour as my ſelfe..</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Art thou able to kéepe theſe comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of thy ſelfe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Of my ſelfe I am not able to kéepe the leaſt of the tenne, if I could tell which it were<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How ſhall we then ſatiſfie the lawe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By Chriſt, for he hath fulfilled it fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Should we liue careles becauſe Chriſt hath fulfilled the lawe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God forbid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> VVhat muſt we doe then?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Learne to pray vnto the Lord God in the only name of his ſonne Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus our Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How muſt it be then that we pray?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thus, Our father which art in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Why doeſt thou call God father?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe by faith in Chriſt we be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen
<pb facs="tcp:2749:14"/>
for the children of God. <hi>Iohn. 1. 12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Why ſayeſt thou our father, and not my father.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe he is not only my father, but alſo the father of all the faithfull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Is God no where but in heauen?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, he is in all places at once, and therefore in our Créede, we call him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> VVhy doth our maiſter Chriſt teach vs to ſay heauen?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe in praying we ſhould lift vp our mindes to heauen whether hee is gone before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> VVhat deſire you in this petition? Hallowed be thy name.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Here we deſire God to giue vs grace that we may reuerently eſtéeme of his holy word which teacheth him vnto vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What more doe we pray for?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That we might liue a holy life agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> VVhat doth Chriſt teach vs to pray for, in this petition? Thy kingdome come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That the loue of God might be amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs, and that his worde which teacheth
<pb facs="tcp:2749:14"/>
him vnto vs, might fréely of vs be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How ſhould this bee knowen, that Gods loue is among vs?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By this, if we haue loue one to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> VVhat more are we taught?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> VVe are alſo taught to pray for a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient wayting for of his comming to iudgment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Are we not alſo in this petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taught to pray for the encreaſe of faith?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yea, for the more that our faith en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth, the more doth Gods kingdom encreaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> In that Chriſt teacheth vs to pray that Gods will may be done, in earth as it is in heauen: what doth he ſéeme to forbid?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In teaching vs ſo to pray, hee woulde not haue vs to ſéeke our owne wils, or to ſticke to our owne wiſedom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Then it foloweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we pray againſt pride, couetouſnes, extortion, vſury, bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, exceſſe, dronkennes, whoredome, theft, lying &amp; ſuch like vices, for theſe be the will of man, &amp; contrarie to the will
<pb facs="tcp:2749:15"/>
of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> VVe doe ſo I confeſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> If we pray againſt thoſe ſinners, and to be endewed with righteouſneſſe, and yet take a delight in them: what doe we?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Euen mocke with God, and ſo doe heape puniſhment vpon our ſelues for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Becauſe I ſée this to be againſt mee, ſhould I not therefore pray?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> If we ſhould not pray, we were the deſpiſers of his commandement. <hi>Mark. 14. 38.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> VVhat are we here taught to aſke? giue vs this day our daily bread.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All thinges neceſſarie to this preſent life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Why doth he teach vs to pray day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for dayly bread?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe without his dayly bleſſing our food could giue ſmall nouriſhment vnto vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What deſire ye in this petition: For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue vs our treſpaſſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Here I deſire his mercy: for vnleſſe he be pitifull vnto vs, we are readie to
<pb facs="tcp:2749:15"/>
fall into vtter deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What meaneth the condition? As we forgiue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Here we deſire, that it may bee his pleaſure to giue vs grace that we may be ready to pardon thoſe that haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Why doe you ſay? Leade vs not into temptation?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Here we pray that God will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vs to be ouercome of temptation: but that being for our profit or tryall, we might boldly bee ſtrengthened in him to abide that which his pleaſure is to lay vpon vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Why is this added? For thine is the kingdome, the power and the glory for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> This doth teach vs to confeſſe that all rule and authoritie doth come from God, and ruleth all thinges according to his will.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> VVhy ſayeſt thou, Amen, in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of the prayer?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By that word I deſire the Lord God to grannt all thinges which before I
<pb facs="tcp:2749:16"/>
prayed for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Tell me the effect in few wordes of all that thou haſt ſaide vpon the Lordes Prayer?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I deſire Gods grace to doe his will, and thinges neceſſarie both to body and ſoule.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer.</head>
               <p>THe Lord giue vs grace to lay theſe thinges vp déepely in our harts, and alwaies to be mindfull of them, as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooueth his true and faithfull Children in Chriſt Ieſus. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2749:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
